	character	Dialoge
2	Hobbit	 You're late!
2	Old Man	 A wizard is never late, Frodo Baggins. Nor is he early. He arrives precisely when he means to.
2	Frodo	 < leaps onto cart and hugs the old man > Its wonderful to see you Gandalf!
2	Gandalf	 < laughs > Ooh! You didn’t think I’d miss your Uncle Bilbo's birthday?
2	Frodo	 What news of the outside world? Tell me everything.
2	Gandalf	 Everything? Far too eager and curious for a hobbit, most unnatural. Well what can I tell you? Life in the wide world goes on much as it has this past age, full of its own comings and goings. Scarcely aware of the existence of hobbits... which I am very thankful.
2	Hobbit folk	 Look it's Gandalf! Its Gandalf!
2	Gandalf	 Ooh! The long expected party!
2	Gandalf	 So how is the old rascal? I hear it’s got to be a party of special magnificence.
2	Frodo	 You know Bilbo, he's got the whole place in an uproar.
2	Gandalf	 Hmm, well now that should please him, hmmm.
3	Frodo	 Half the Shire’s been invited.
3	Gandalf	 Good gracious me!
3	Frodo	 He is up to something.
3	Gandalf	 Oh really…
3	Frodo	 All right then keep your secrets. < Gandalf laughs > Before you came along we Bagginses were very well thought of.
3	Gandalf	 Indeed?
3	Frodo	 Never had any adventures or did anything unexpected.
3	Gandalf	 If you’re referring to the incident with the dragon, I was barely involved. All I did was give your uncle a little nudge out of the door.
3	Frodo	 Whatever you did, you’ve been officially labeled a disturber of the peace.
3	Gandalf	 Oh really?
3	Hobbit children	 Gandalf! Gandalf! Fireworks? Gandalf?
3	Hobbit children	 < dissapointed > Awwww.
4	Frodo	 Gandalf, I'm glad you're back.
4	Gandalf	 < as Frodo jumps off the cart > So am I, dear boy! So am I.
5	Bilbo	 < from within > No thank you! We don't want any more visitors, well-wishers or distant relations!
5	Gandalf	 And what about very old friends?
5	Bilbo	 Gandalf?
5	Gandalf	 Bilbo Baggins!
5	Bilbo	 My dear Gandalf! < gives Gandalf a hug >
5	Gandalf	 Good to see you! One hundred and eleven years old --who would believe it? < looks at Bilbo in astonishment > You haven't aged a day.
6	Bilbo	 Come on, come in! Welcome, welcome! < closes door > *There we are/ *Well now. Tea? Or maybe something a little stronger? I've got a few bottles of the Old Winyard left. 1296 --very good year. Almost as old as I am! Hahaha! It was laid down by my father. What say we open one, eh? [*note to reader
6	Gandalf	 Just tea, thank you.
6	Bilbo	 I was expecting you here last week! Not that it matters, you come and go as you please. Always have done and always will. You caught me a bit unprepared, I'm afraid. We have some cold chicken and pickles... Here's some cheese here- oh no it won't do. There we got raspberry jam and apple tart... Not much for afterlunch - oh no! We're all right. I have some cake. < enters the study > I can make you some eggs if you like-- oh. Gandalf?
6	Gandalf	 Just tea, thank you.
6	Bilbo	 Alright! < with mouthful of cake > You don't mind if I eat, do you?
6	Gandalf	 Oh no, not at all.
6	Bilbo	 < whispers > I'm not at home!
6	Bilbo	 I've got to get away from these confounded relatives hanging on the bell--they never give me a moment's peace! I want to see mountains again, mountains Gandalf! And then find somewhere quiet where I can finish my book. Oh, tea!
6	Gandalf	 So, you mean to go through with your plan, then.
6	Bilbo	 Yes, yes. It's all in hand. All the arrangements are made. < starts to pour water into the tea pot, Gandalf opens the lid > Oh, thank you.
6	Gandalf	 Frodo suspects something.
6	Bilbo	 ‘Course he does. He's a Baggins! Not some block-headed Bracegirdle from Hardbottle.
6	Gandalf	 You will tell him, won't you?
6	Bilbo	 Yes, yes.
6	Gandalf	 He's very fond of you.
6	Bilbo	 I know. He'd probably come with me if I asked him < chuckles >. I think in his heart Frodo is still in love with the Shire
7	Bilbo	 Old Toby. The finest weed in the Southfarthing.
7	Bilbo	 Gandalf, my old friend. This will be a night to remember!
7	Bilbo	 < to guest > Hello, hello, Fatty Bolger, lovely to see you! Welcome, welcome!
8	Frodo	 < sits beside him > Go on Sam! Ask Rosie for a dance.
8	Sam	 < gets cold feet > I think I’ll just have another ale.
8	Frodo	 Oh no you don’t. Go on. < pushes Sam to the dance floor and into Rosie’s arms. Frodo laughs aloud >
8	Gandalf	 < setting off a firework > Whoa!
8	Bilbo	 There I was, at the mercy of three monstrous trolls! And they were all arguing amongst themselves about how they were going to cook us, whether it be turned on a spit or whether they should sit on us one by one and squash us into jelly.
8	Bilbo	 They spent so much time arguing the wither-tos and why-fors, that when the sun’s first light cracked over the top of the trees and poof!
8	Hobbit Children	 < gasp >
8	Bilbo	 It turned them all to stone!
8	Merry	 Quickly!
8	Gandalf	 Whoa! Off they go.
8	Merry	 No, no the big one, big one
8	Pippin	 Done.
8	Merry	 You’re supposed to stick it in the ground!
8	Pippin	 It is in the ground.
8	Merry	 Outside!
8	Pippin	 It was your idea!
8	Hobbit	 Look at that!
8	Frodo	 Bilbo? Bilbo, look out for the dragon!
8	Bilbo	 Dragon? Nonsense! There hasn’t been a dragon in these parts for a thousand years…
8	Merry	 That was good!
8	Pippin	 Let’s get another one!
8	Merry and Pippin	 Aah!
8	Gandalf	 Meriadoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took. I might have known.
8	Hobbits	 Speech, Bilbo! Speech!
8	Frodo	 Speech!
8	Bilbo	 My dear Bagginses and Boffins, < cheers > Tooks and Brandybucks, < cheers > Grubbs, < cheers > Chubbs, < cheers > Hornblowers, < cheers > Bolgers, < cheers > Bracegirdles < cheers > and Proudfoots.
8	Proudfoot Hobbit	 Proudfeet!
8	Bilbo	 Today is my 111th birthday!
8	Hobbits	 Happy birthday!
8	Hobbit	 Happy birthday!
8	Bilbo	 Alas, eleventy-one years is far too short a time to live among such excellent and admirable hobbits. < cheers > I don’t know half of you half as well as I should like, and I like less than half of you half as well as you deserve. < dead silence from the crowd >
8	Bilbo	 I, uh, I h-have things to do. < fidgets with the Ring behind his back. Whispers to himself > I’ve put this off for far too long. < to the crowd > I regret to announce this is the end. I am going now. I bid you all a very fond farewell. < whispers >Goodbye.
8	Hobbits	 < shocked > Ooh!
8	Bilbo	 Hahahahaha! < flips the ring, catches it and puts it in his pocket >
10	Gandalf	 I suppose you think that was terribly clever.
10	Bilbo	 Come on Gandalf! Did you see their faces?
10	Gandalf	 There are many magic rings in this world Bilbo Baggins and none of them should be used lightly.
10	Bilbo	 It was just a bit of fun! Oh you’re probably right, as usual. You will keep an eye on Frodo, won’t you?
10	Gandalf	 Two eyes, as often as I can spare them.
10	Bilbo	 I’m leaving everything to him.
10	Gandalf	 What about this Ring of yours, is that staying too?
10	Bilbo	 Yes, yes. It’s in an envelope over there on the mantelpiece. < Gandalf turns to look >
10	Bilbo	 No, wait, its --here in my pocket. Heh, isn’t that, isn’t that odd though? < looks at the Ring > Yet, after all why not? Why shouldn’t I keep it?
10	Gandalf	 I think you should leave the Ring behind, Bilbo. Is that so hard?
10	Bilbo	 Well no… and yes! Now it comes to it, I don’t feel like parting with it, its mine, I found it, it came to me!
10	Gandalf	 There’s no need to get angry.
10	Bilbo	 What if I’m angry, it’s your fault! < caresses Ring > It’s mine! My own, my precious.
10	Gandalf	 Precious? Its been called that before, but not by you.
10	Bilbo	 Argh! What business is it of yours what I do with my own things!
10	Gandalf	 I think you’ve had that Ring quite long enough.
10	Bilbo	 You want it for yourself!
10	Gandalf	 Bilbo Baggins! Do not take me for some conjurer of cheap tricks. I am not trying to rob you. I’m trying to help you.
10	Bilbo	 < starts weeping >
10	Gandalf	 All your long years we’ve been friends. Trust me as you once did, hmm? Let it go.
10	Bilbo	 < collects himself > You’re right Gandalf, the Ring must go to Frodo. It’s late, the road is long. Yes it is time.
10	Gandalf	 Bilbo…
10	Bilbo	 Hmm?
10	Gandalf	 …the Ring is still in your pocket.
10	Bilbo	 Oh, yes…
11	Bilbo	" I’ve thought of an ending for my book. < turns to Gandalf at the door > ""And he lived happily ever after…to the end of his days""."
11	Gandalf	 And I’m sure you will my dear friend.
11	Bilbo	 Good bye, Gandalf.
11	Gandalf	 Good bye, dear Bilbo.
11	Bilbo	 The road goes ever on and on, down from the door where it began…
11	Gandalf	 Until our next meeting.
11	Gandalf	 < mumbles > Riddles in the Dark.
11	Frodo	 Bilbo! Bilbo!
11	Gandalf	 < mumbles > My precious.
11	Gandalf	 < mumbles > Precious…
11	Frodo	 He's gone hasn't he? He talked for so long about leaving. I didn't think he'd really do it.
11	Frodo	 Gandalf?
11	Gandalf	 Hmm. < smiles at Frodo > Bilbo's Ring. He's gone to stay with the elves. He's left you Bag End… < holds envelope open, Frodo slips in the Ring, Gandalf seals the envelope > …along with all his possessions. The Ring is yours now. Put it somewhere out of sight.
11	Frodo	 Where are you going?
11	Gandalf	 There are some things that I must see to.
11	Frodo	 What things?
11	Gandalf	 Questions. Questions that need answering!
11	Frodo	 But you've only just arrived! I don't understand.
11	Gandalf	 < looks back at Frodo > Neither do I. Keep it secret. Keep it safe.
11	Gollum	 Shire!!! Baggins!!!
17	Gandalf	 < voice over >Year 3434 of the Second Age. Here follows the account of Isildur, High King of Gondor and the finding of the Ring of Power. It has come to me, the One Ring. It shall be an heirloom of my kingdom. All that should follow in my bloodline shall be bound to its fate for I will risk no hurt to the Ring. It is precious to me, though I buy it with a great pain. The markings upon the band begin to fade. The writing, which at first was as clear as red flame, has all but disappeared. A secret now that only fire can tell.
18	Ringwraith	 Shire. Baggins.
18	Hobbit	 < fearful > Baggins. There are no Baggins ‘round here. They’re up in Hobbiton, that way. < points >
18	Rosie	 Goodnight.
18	Sam	 Goodnight.
18	Sam	 Goodnight.
18	Frodo	 Goodnight Sam.
18	Frodo	 < startled > Huh?!
21	Gandalf	 Is it secret?! Is it safe?!
22	Frodo	 Ah! < hands Gandalf the envelope >
22	Frodo	 < alarmed > What are you doing?
22	Gandalf	 Hold out your hand Frodo, it’s quite cool. < drops the Ring on Frodo’s hand > What can you see? Can you see anything?
22	Frodo	 Nothing. There's nothing... wait. There are markings. It's some form of elvish. I can’t read it.
22	Gandalf	 There are few who can. The language is that of Mordor, which I will not utter here.
22	Frodo	 Mordor?
22	Gandalf	" In the common tongue it says, ""One Ring to rule them all, One Ring to find them. One Ring to bring them all and in the darkness bind them."""
23	Gandalf	 This is the One Ring. Forged by the Dark Lord Sauron in the fires of Mount Doom. Taken by Isildur from the hand of Sauron himself.
23	Frodo	 Bilbo found it. In Gollum's cave.
23	Gandalf	 Yes. For sixty years the Ring lay quiet in Bilbo's keeping, prolonging his life, delaying old age. But no longer Frodo. Evil is stirring in Mordor. The Ring has awoken. It's heard its master's call.
23	Frodo	 But he was destroyed. Sauron was destroyed.
23	Ring	 < whispers > Isildur…
23	Gandalf	 No, Frodo. The spirit of Sauron endured. His life force is bound to the Ring and the Ring survived. Sauron has returned. His orcs have multiplied. His fortress of Barad-Dur is rebuilt in the land of Mordor. Sauron needs only this Ring to cover all the lands of a second darkness. He is seeking it. Seeking it, all his thought is bent on it. The Ring yearns above all else to return to the hand of its master. They are one, the Ring and the Dark Lord. Frodo, he must never find it.
24	Frodo	 Alright, we put it away. We keep it hidden. We never speak of it again. No one knows it's here, do they? Do they Gandalf?
25	Gandalf	 There is one other who knew that Bilbo had the Ring. I looked everywhere for the creature Gollum. But the enemy found him first. I don’t know how long they tortured him. Amidst the endless screams and inane babble, they discerned two words
25	Gollum	 Shire!!! Baggins!!!
26	Frodo	 Shire. Baggins. But that would lead them here!
27	Hobbit	 Who goes there?
28	Frodo	 Take it Gandalf! Take it!
28	Gandalf	 No Frodo no.
28	Frodo	 You must take it!
28	Gandalf	 You cannot offer me this Ring!
28	Frodo	 I'm giving it to you!
28	Gandalf	 Don't tempt me Frodo! I dare not take it. Not even to keep it safe. Understand Frodo, I would use this Ring from the desire to do good. But through me, it would wield a power to great and terrible to imagine.
28	Frodo	 But it cannot stay in the Shire!
28	Gandalf	 No! No it can't.
28	Frodo	 What must I do?
29	Gandalf	 You must leave and leave quickly.
29	Frodo	 Where? Where do I go?
29	Gandalf	 Get out of the Shire. Make for the village Bree.
29	Frodo	 Bree. What about you?
29	Gandalf	 I'll be waiting for you, at the Inn of the Prancing Pony.
29	Frodo	 And the Ring will be safe there?
29	Gandalf	 I don't know Frodo. I don't have any answers. I must see the head of my order. He is both wise and powerful. Trust me Frodo, he’ll know what to do. 
30	Gandalf	You’ll have to leave the name of Baggins behind you
30	Frodo	 I can cut across country easily enough.
30	Gandalf	 My dear Frodo. Hobbits really are amazing creatures! You can learn all that there is to know about their ways in a month, and yet after a hundred years, they can still surprise you. < hears rustling of the leaves > Get down!
30	Sam	 Oooff!!
30	Gandalf	 Confound it all Samwise Gamgee! Have you been eavesdropping?!
30	Sam	 I have been droppin’ no eves sir, honest. I was just cutting the grass under the window there, if you follow me.
30	Gandalf	 A little late for trimming the verge don’t you think?
30	Sam	 I heard raised voices.
30	Gandalf	 What did you hear?! Speak!!!!
30	Sam	 N-n-n-nothing important. That is I heard a good deal about a Ring and a Dark Lord and something about the end of the world but… Please, Mister Gandalf sir, don’t hurt me. Don’t turn me into anythin’ --unnatural.
30	Gandalf	 No, perhaps not. I have thought of a better use for you…
31	Gandalf	 Come along Samwise, keep up! 
32	Gandalf	Be careful both of you. The enemy has many spies in his service
34	Sam	 This is it.
34	Frodo	 < turns > This is what?
34	Sam	 I take one more step, it’ll be the farthest away from home I’ve ever been.
34	Frodo	 < reassuringly > Come on Sam. Remember what Bilbo used to say
36	Saruman	 Smoke rises from the mountain of Doom. The hour grows late and Gandalf the Grey rides to Isengard seeking my counsel. For that is why you have come, is it not...my old friend?
36	Gandalf	 Saruman. < bows >
37	Saruman	 You are sure of this?
37	Gandalf	 Beyond any doubt.
37	Saruman	 The Ring of Power has been found.
37	Gandalf	 All these long years it was in the Shire, under my very nose.
37	Saruman	 Yet you did not have the wit to see it. Your love of the halfling’s leaf has clearly slowed your mind.
37	Gandalf	 But we still have time. Time enough to counter Sauron if we act quickly.
37	Saruman	 Time?! What time do you think we have?
38	Saruman	 Sauron has regained much of his former strength. He cannot yet take physical form, but his spirit has lost none of its potency. Concealed within his fortress, the Lord of Mordor sees all -- his gaze pierces cloud, shadow, earth and flesh. You know of what I speak, Gandalf -- a great Eye... lidless... wreathed in flame.
38	Gandalf	 The Eye of Sauron.
38	Saruman	 He is gathering all evil to him. Very soon he will summon an army great enough to launch an assault upon Middle Earth.
38	Gandalf	 You know this? How?
38	Saruman	 I have seen it.
38	Gandalf	 A Palantir is a dangerous tool, Saruman.
38	Saruman	 Why? Why should we fear to use it?
38	Gandalf	 They are not all accounted for, the lost Seeing Stones. We do not know who else may be watching!
38	Saruman	 The hour is later than you think. Sauron's forces are already moving. The Nine have left Minas Morgul.
38	Gandalf	 < alarmed > The Nine!
38	Saruman	 They crossed the River Isen on Midsummer's Eve, disguised as riders in black.
38	Gandalf	 They've reached the Shire?!
38	Saruman	 They will find the Ring… and kill the one who carries it.
38	Gandalf	 Frodo!
38	Saruman	 You did not seriously think that a hobbit could contend with the will of Sauron? There are none who can. Against the power of Mordor there can be no victory. We must join with him, Gandalf. We must join with Sauron. It would be wise, my friend.
38	Gandalf	" Tell me, ""friend"", when did Saruman the wise abandon reason for madness?!"
38	Saruman	 I gave you the chance of aiding me willingly. But you...have elected...the way of pain!
39	Sam	 < starts to panic > Mister Frodo? Frodo! Frodo!
39	Sam	 < sigh > I thought I’d lost you.
39	Frodo	 What are you talking about?
39	Sam	 It's just something Gandalf said.
39	Frodo	 What did he say?
39	Sam	" ""Don’t you lose him Samwise Gamgee!"" And I don't mean to."
39	Frodo	 < amused > Sam, we're still in the Shire. What could possibly happen?
39	Pippin	 Frodo? Merry! It's Frodo Baggins.
39	Merry	 Hello Frodo!
39	Sam	 Get off him! < hauls Pippin off Frodo > Frodo? Are you all right?
39	Pippin	 What's the meaning of this?
39	Merry	 Hold this. < hands vegetables to Sam >
39	Sam	 You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
39	Farmer Maggot	 < brandishing a scythe > Wait till I get this through you!…Stay out of my fields! You ruffians I’ll catch up with you!
39	Merry	 ‘Dunno why he is so upset. It’s only a couple of carrots!
39	Pippin	 And some cabbages. And those few bags of potatoes that we lifted last week and, and the mushrooms the week before!
39	Merry	 Yes Pippin! My point is, he is clearly overreactin’. Run!
40	Pippin	 Ooh! That was close
40	Merry	 Ow! I think I've broken something. < pulls out a broken carrot >
40	Sam	 Trust a Brandybuck and a Took!
40	Merry	 What?! That was just a detour, a shortcut.
40	Sam	 A shortcut to what?
40	Pippin	 Mushrooms!!!
40	Pippin	 That’s mine!
40	Hobbits	 Mmm…
40	Merry	 Here is a nice one Sam.
40	Frodo	 I think we should get off the road.
40	Frodo	 Get off the road! Quick!
40	Sam	 Shhh! < to Merry and Pippin > Stop it! Be quiet!
40	Merry	 What was that?
41	Pippin	 Anything?
41	Frodo	 Nothing.
41	Pippin	 What is going on?
41	Merry	 That Black Rider was looking for something… or someone. Frodo?
41	Sam	 Get down!
41	Frodo	 I have to leave the Shire. Sam and I must get to Bree.
41	Merry	 Right. Buckleberry Ferry. Follow me.
41	Pippin	 Run! This way, follow me! Run!
42	Merry	 Get the rope Sam!
42	Sam	 Frodo!
42	Hobbits	 Run Frodo!
42	Frodo	 Go!
42	Hobbits	 Hurry!
42	Sam	 Frodo!
42	Hobbits	 Jump Frodo! Go on faster! Jump!
42	Frodo	 How far to the nearest crossing?
42	Merry	 Brandywine Bridge
43	Frodo	 Come on.
43	Gatekeeper	 What do you want?
43	Frodo	 We’re heading for the Prancing Pony.
43	Gatekeeper	 Hobbits! Four hobbits! What business brings you to Bree?
43	Frodo	 We wish to stay at the inn. Our business is our own.
43	Gatekeeper	 Alright young sir, I meant no offence. ‘Tis my job to ask question after nightfall. There’s talk of strange folk abroad. Can’t be too careful.
43	Men of Bree	 Move! Watch where you're going!
45	Frodo	 Excuse me?
45	Butterbur	 Good evening little masters! If you’re seeking accommodation we’ve got some nice, cozy, hobbit-sized rooms available. Mr. uh--
45	Frodo	 --Underhill, my name’s Underhill.
45	Butterbur	 Underhill. Hmm.
45	Frodo	 We’re friends of Gandalf the Grey. Can you tell him we’ve arrived?
45	Butterbur	 Gandalf? Gandalf? Ohhh yes! I remember, elderly chap, big gray beard, pointy hat. Not seen him for 6 months.
45	Sam	 What do we do now?
46	Frodo	 Sam. He’ll be here. He’ll come.
46	Man	 < to Merry coming from the bar > Get, get out of my way.
46	Pippin	 What’s that?
46	Merry	 This my friend, is a pint.
46	Pippin	 It comes in pints? I’m getting one. < rushes to the bar >
46	Sam	 You had a whole half already!
46	Sam	 That fellow’s done nothin’ but starin’ at us since we arrived.
46	Frodo	 < takes Barliman aside > Excuse me, that man in the corner, who is he?
46	Butterbur	 He’s one of them rangers. Dangerous folk they are-- all wandering the wilds. What his right name is I’ve never heard but around here, he’s known as Strider.
46	Frodo	 Strider...
46	The Ring	 Baggins. Baggins. Baggins. Baggins! Baggins!…
46	Pippin	 Baggins!
46	Pippin	" < at the bar > Sure I know a Baggins. He’s over there, Frodo Baggins. He's my second cousin once removed on his mother's side < listeners laugh, ""It works for him!"" yells one > and my third cousin twice removed on his father's side, if you follow me."
46	Frodo	 Pippin! < grabs him >
46	Pippin	 Steady on!
46	Voice of Sauron	 You cannot hide! I see you! There is no life in the void, only death!
46	Frodo	 Ah! < Strider grabs him from behind >
49	Strider	" You draw far too much attention to yourself Mr. ""Underhill""! < tosses him up the stairs >"
50	Frodo	 What do you want?
50	Strider	 A little more caution from you. That is no trinket you carry.
50	Frodo	 I carry nothing.
50	Strider	 Indeed.
50	Strider	 I can avoid being seen if I wish. But to disappear entirely, that is a rare gift.
50	Frodo	 Who are you?
50	Strider	 Are you frightened?
50	Frodo	 Yes.
50	Strider	 Not nearly frightened enough. I know what hunts you.
50	Sam	 *Stand off! / *Let him go! Or I’ll have you Longshanks! [*note to reader
50	Strider	 You have a stout heart little hobbit, but that will not save you. You can no longer wait for the wizard Frodo. They’re coming.
57	Frodo	 What are they?
57	Strider	 They were once men. Great kings of Men. Then Sauron the Deceiver gave to them nine Rings of Power. Blinded by their greed, they took them without question. One by one falling into darkness. Now they are slaves to his will. They are the Nazgul, Ringwraiths, neither living nor dead. At all times they feel the presence of the Ring. Drawn to the power of the One. They will never stop hunting you.
58	Frodo	 Where are you taking us?
58	Strider	 Into the wild.
58	Merry	 < to Frodo > How do we know this Strider is a friend of Gandalf’s?
58	Frodo	 We have no choice but to trust him.
58	Sam	 But where is he leading us?
58	Strider	 To Rivendell Master Gamgee, The House of Elrond.
58	Sam	 Did you hear that? Rivendell! We’re going to see the elves!
59	Strider	 Gentlemen, we do not stop till nightfall.
59	Pippin	 What about breakfast?
59	Strider	 We’ve already had it.
59	Pippin	 We've had one yes. What about second breakfast?
59	Merry	 Don't think he knows about second breakfast Pip.
59	Pippin	 < alarmed > What about elevenses? Luncheon? Afternoon tea? Dinner? Supper? He knows about them doesn’t he?
59	Merry	 I wouldn't count on it.
59	Merry	 < impatiently > Pippin!
60	Saruman	 < telepathically > The power of Isengard is at your command, Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
60	Voice of Sauron	 Build me an army worthy of Mordor!
61	Orc	 What orders from Mordor my Lord? What does the Eye command?
61	Saruman	 We have work to do!
62	Orcs	 The trees are strong, my Lord. Their roots go deep.
62	Saruman	 Rip them all down.
63	Strider	 This was the great watchtower of Amon Sul. We shall rest here tonight.
64	Strider	 These are for you. Keep them close. I’m going to have a look around. Stay here.
65	Pippin	 Can I have some meat?
65	Merry	 Ok. Want some tomatoes Sam?
65	Merry	 Great tomatoes
65	Frodo	 What are you doing?!
65	Merry	 Tomatoes, sausages, nice crispy bacon.
65	Sam	 We saved some for you Mr. Frodo.
65	Frodo	 Put it out you fools! Put it out!
65	Pippin	 Oh that’s nice! Ash on my tomatoes!
65	All	 Uh?!
65	Frodo	 Go!
66	Sam	 < brandishing his sword > Back you devils!
66	Frodo	 Aaaahhhh!
66	Sam	 Frodo! < rushes to his side >
66	Frodo	 Oh Sam!
66	Sam	 Strider! Help him Strider.
66	Strider	 He’s been stabbed by a Morgul blade. < blade dissolves in the wind > This is beyond my skill to heal. He needs elvish medicine.
67	Strider	 Hurry!
67	Sam	 We are six days from Rivendell. He’ll never make it!
67	Frodo	 < whispering > Gandalf…
67	Strider	 Hold on Frodo.
67	Frodo	 < cries out > …Gandalf!!!!
67	Gandalf	 < whispering > Gwaihir. Go, Gwaihir.
67	Sam	 Mr. Frodo? < to Strider > He’s going cold!
70	Pippin	 Is he going to die?
70	Strider	 He’s passing into the shadow world. He will soon become a wraith like them.
70	Merry	 They’re close.
70	Strider	 Sam, do you know Athelas plant?
70	Sam	 Athelas?
70	Strider	 Kingsfoil.
70	Sam	 Kingsfoil- uh, that's a weed.
70	Strider	 It may help to slow the poison. Hurry!
71	Arwen	 What’s this? A ranger caught off his guard?
72	Arwen	 Frodo.... Im Arwen. Telin le thaed (I am Arwen. I have come to help you.)
72	Arwen	 Lasto beth nin. Tolo dan na galad (Hear my voice. Come back to the light)
72	Merry	 < in awe > Who is she?
72	Arwen	 < kneels > Frodo!
72	Sam	 She's an elf.
72	Arwen	 He's fading!
72	Arwen	 He's not going to last. We must get him to my father. I’ve been looking for you for 2 days.
72	Merry	 Where are you taking him?
72	Arwen	 There are 5 wraiths behind you. Where the other 4 are, I do not know.
72	Strider/Aragorn	 Dartho guin perian. Rych le ad tolthathon. (Stay with the Hobbits. I will send horses again for you)
72	Arwen	 Hon mabathon. Rochon ellint im. (I’m the faster rider. I’ll take him.)
72	Strider/Aragorn	 Andelu i ven. (The road is too dangerous.)
72	Pippin	 What are they saying?
72	Arwen	 Frodo fir. Ae athradon i hir, tur gwaith nin beriatha hon. (If I can get across the river, the power of my people will protect him.)
72	Arwen	 < reassuringly > I do not fear them.
72	Strider/Aragorn	 Beyest lin.
72	Strider/Aragorn	 Arwen, ride hard. Don’t look back!
76	Arwen	 Noro lim, Asfaloth, noro lim! (Ride fast Asfaloth, ride fast!)
76	Sam	 < to Strider > What are you doing?! Those wraiths are still out there!
76	Arwen	 Noro lim Asfaloth!!! (Ride faster Asfaloth!)
77	Nazgul	 Give up the half-fling she-elf!
77	Arwen	 < draws her sword > If you want him, come and claim him!
77	Arwen	 Nin o Chithaeglir, lasto beth daer, Rimmo nin Bruinen dan in Ulair!
77	Arwen	 No! Frodo...No! Frodo, don’t give in! Not now!
78	Arwen	 < voice over > What grace is given me, let it pass to him, let him be spared, save him.
78	Elrond	 Lasto beth nin. Tolo dan nan galad. (Hear my voice, come back to the light)
78	Frodo	 < half-asleep > Where am I?
78	Gandalf	 You are in the house of Elrond. And it is 10 o’clock in the morning, on October the 24th if you want to know.
79	Frodo	 Gandalf!
79	Gandalf	 Yes...I’m here. And you're lucky to be here too. A few more hours and you would have been beyond our aid. But you have some strength in you, my dear hobbit!
79	Frodo	 What happened Gandalf? Why didn't you meet us?
79	Gandalf	 Oh I'm sorry Frodo... I was delayed.
80	Saruman	 Friendship with Saruman is not lightly thrown aside.
80	Saruman	 One ill turn deserves another. It is over! Embrace the power of the Ring…or embrace your own destruction!
80	Gandalf	 < slowly raises himself > There is only one Lord of the Ring! Only one can bend it to his will. And he does not share power!
80	Saruman	 So you have chosen - death.
82	Frodo	 Gandalf? What is it?
82	Gandalf	 Nothing Frodo.
82	Sam	 Frodo! Frodo!
82	Frodo	 Sam!
82	Sam	 Bless you, you're awake!
82	Gandalf	 Sam has hardly left your side.
82	Sam	 We were that worried about you, weren't we Mr. Gandalf?
82	Gandalf	 By the skills of Lord Elrond, you're beginning to mend.
82	Elrond	 Welcome to Rivendell, Frodo Baggins.
84	Frodo	 Bilbo!
85	Bilbo	 Hello Frodo my lad!
85	Frodo	 Bilbo! < hug >
85	Bilbo	 Oh!
85	Frodo	" ""There and Back Again"
85	Bilbo	 I meant to go back...wander the paths of Mirkwood... visit Laketown...see the Lonely Mountain again. But age it seems have finally caught up with me. < gives Frodo a playful smirk >
85	Frodo	 I miss the Shire. I spent all my childhood, pretending I was off somewhere else…off with you on one of your adventures! < realizes sadly > My own adventure turned out to be quite different.
85	Frodo	 I’m not like you Bilbo.
85	Bilbo	 My dear boy.
86	Sam	 < to himself > Now what have I forgotten?
86	Frodo	 Packed already?
86	Sam	 No harm in being prepared.
86	Frodo	 I thought you wanted to see the elves Sam.
86	Sam	 I do!
86	Frodo	 More than anything.
86	Sam	 I did! Its just...we did what Gandalf wanted didn't we? We got the Ring this far to Rivendell and then I thought, seen’ as how you’re on the mend, we'd be off soon. Off home.
86	Frodo	 You're right Sam. We did what we set out to do. < shows the Ring on his palm > The Ring will be safe in Rivendell.
86	Frodo	 I am ready to go home.
87	Elrond	 His strength returns.
87	Gandalf	 That wound will never fully heal. He will carry it the rest of his life.
87	Elrond	 And yet to have come so far, still bearing the Ring, the hobbit has shown extraordinary resilience to it's evil.
87	Gandalf	 It is a burden he should never have had to bear. We can ask no more of Frodo.
87	Elrond	 Gandalf, the enemy is moving. Sauron's forces are amassing in the east-- his eye is fixed on Rivendell. And Saruman you tell me has betrayed us. Our list of allies grows thin.
87	Gandalf	 His treachery runs deeper than you know. By foul craft Saruman has crossed orcs with goblin-men, he's breeding an army in the caverns of Isengard. An army that can move in sunlight and cover great distance at speed. Saruman is coming for the Ring.
87	Elrond	 This evil cannot be concealed by the power of the Elves. We do not have the strength to fight both Mordor and Isengard!
87	Elrond	 Gandalf, the Ring cannot stay here.
87	Elrond	 This peril belongs to all middle earth. They must decide now how to end it. The time of the Elves is over-- my people are leaving these shores. Who will you look to when we've gone? The Dwarves? They hide in their mountains seeking riches-- they care nothing for the troubles of others.
87	Gandalf	 It is in Men that we must place our hope.
87	Elrond	 Men? Men are weak. The race of men is failing. The blood of Numenor is all but spent. It's pride and dignity forgotten. It is because of men the Ring survives. I was there Gandalf. I was there three thousand years ago…
87	Elrond	 Isildur took the Ring. I was there the day the strength of men failed.
88	Elrond	 Isildur hurry. Follow me.
88	Elrond	 < voice over > I led Isildur into the heart of Mount Doom, where the Ring was forged, the one place it could be destroyed.
88	Elrond	 Cast it into the fire!
88	Elrond	 Destroy it!
88	Isildur	 No.
88	Elrond	 Isildur!!!
89	Elrond	 < voice over > It should’ve ended that day, but evil was allowed to endure.
89	Elrond	 Isildur kept the Ring. The line of kings is broken. There is no strength left in the world of men. They’re scattered, divided, leaderless.
89	Gandalf	 There is one who could unite them, one who could reclaim the throne of Gondor.
89	Elrond	 He turned from that path long time ago. He has chosen exile.
90	Boromir	 The shards of Narsil! The blade that cut the ring from Sauron's hand!
90	Boromir	 < in amazement > It's still sharp!
90	Boromir	 < in disdain > No more than a broken heirloom!
90	Arwen	 Why do you fear the past? You are Isildur's heir, not Isildur himself. You are not bound to his fate.
90	Aragorn	 The same blood flows in my veins. < turns to Arwen > Same weakness.
90	Arwen	 Your time will come. You will face the same evil, and you will defeat it. A si i-Dhúath ú-orthor. Ú or le a ú or nin. (The Shadow does not hold sway yet, not over you and not over me.)
92	Arwen	 Renech i lu i erui govannen? (Do you remember when we first met?)
92	Aragorn	 Nauthannem i ned ol reniannen. (I thought I had strayed into a dream.)
92	Arwen	 < tenderly touches Aragorn’s cheek > Gwenwin in enninath...U-arnech in naeth i si celich. (Long years have passed…You did not have the cares you carry now.)
92	Arwen	 Renech i beth i pennen? (Do you remember what I told you?)
92	Aragorn	 < his fingers run across the Evenstar pendant > You said you'd bind yourself to me. Forsaking the immortal life of your people.
92	Arwen	 And to that I hold. I would rather share one lifetime with you than face all the ages of this world alone.
92	Arwen	 I choose a mortal life.
92	Aragorn	 You cannot give me this!
92	Arwen	 It is mine to give to whom I will...like my heart.
93	Elrond	 Strangers from distant lands, friends of old. You have been summoned here to answer the threat of Mordor. Middle-Earth stands upon the brink of destruction. None can escape it. You will unite or you will fall. Each race is bound to this fate--this one doom. < gestures to the pedestal > Bring forth the Ring, Frodo.
93	Boromir	 So it is true...
93	Man of Laketown	 The Doom of Men
93	Boromir	 < shakes head > It is a gift. A gift to the foes of Mordor. Why not use this Ring? < paces > Long has my father, the Steward of Gondor, kept the forces of Mordor at bay. By the blood of our people are your lands kept safe! Give Gondor the weapon of the enemy. Let us use it against him!
93	Aragorn	 You cannot wield it! None of us can. The One Ring answers to Sauron alone. It has no other master.
93	Boromir	 And what would a ranger know of this matter?
93	Legolas	 This is no mere ranger. He is Aragorn, son of Arathorn. You owe him your allegiance.
93	Boromir	 Aragorn? This... is Isildur's heir?
93	Legolas	 And heir to the throne of Gondor.
93	Aragorn	 Havo dad Legolas (Sit down Legolas)
93	Boromir	 Gondor has no king. Gondor needs no king. < returns to his seat >
93	Gandalf	 Aragorn is right. We cannot use it.
93	Elrond	 You have only one choice. The Ring must be destroyed.
93	Gimli	 What are we waiting for?
93	Gimli	 ARGH!!!!
93	Elrond	 The Ring cannot be destroyed, Gimli, son of Gloin by any craft that we here possess. The Ring was made in the fires of Mount Doom. Only there can it be unmade. It must be taken deep into Mordor and cast back into the fiery chasm from whence it came.
93	Elrond	 One of you must do this.
93	Boromir	 One does not simply walk into Mordor. Its black gates are guarded by more than just orcs. There is evil there that does not sleep. And the great Eye is ever watchful. It is a barren wasteland. Riddled with fire and ash and dust. The very air you breathe is a poisonous fume. Not with ten thousand men could you do this. It is folly!
93	Legolas	 < stands indignantly > Have you heard nothing Lord Elrond has said? The Ring must be destroyed!
93	Gimli	 < leaps to his feet > And I suppose you think you're the one to do it?!
93	Boromir	 < rises > And if we fail, what then?! What happens when Sauron takes back what is his?!
93	Gimli	 I will be dead before I see the Ring in the hands of an elf!
93	Gimli	 Never trust an elf!
93	Gandalf	 Do you not understand that while we bicker amongst ourselves, Sauron's power grows?! None can escape it!
93	Ring	 Ash Nazg Durbatuluk! Ash Nazg Gimbatul! Ash Nazg Gimbatul! Ash Nazg Gimbatul!
93	Frodo	 I will take it! I will take it!
93	Frodo	 I will take the Ring to Mordor. Though-- I do not know the way.
93	Gandalf	 < walks towards Frodo > I will help you bear this burden, Frodo Baggins, so long as it is yours to bear. < places his hands reassuringly on Frodo’s shoulders >
93	Aragorn	 < rises > If by my life or death, I can protect you, I will.
93	Aragorn	 You have my sword.
93	Legolas	 And you have my bow. < walks to join them >
93	Gimli	 And my axe! < looks grimly at Legolas as he joins the group >
93	Boromir	 < walks over to them > You carry the fates of us all little one. If this is indeed the will of the council, then Gondor will see it done.
93	Sam	 Heh! < jumps from behind the bushes and joins them > Mr. Frodo is not goin’ anywhere without me!
93	Elrond	 < amused > No indeed, it is hardly possible to separate you even when he is summoned to a secret council and you are not.
93	Pippin and Merry	 < emerges from behind the pillars to join them > Wait! We are coming too!
93	Merry	 You'd have to send us home tied up in a sack to stop us!
93	Pippin	 Anyway you need people of intelligence on this sort of mission, quest... thing.
93	Merry	 Well that rules you out Pip.
93	Elrond	 Nine companions... So be it! You shall be the Fellowship of the Ring!
93	Pippin	 Great! Where are we going?
94	Bilbo	 My old sword, Sting! Here! Take it, take it!
94	Frodo	 It’s so light!
94	Bilbo	 Yes...yea--made by the elves you know. The blade glows blue when orcs are close. And its times like that my lad, when you'll have to be extra careful!
94	Bilbo	 Here’s a pretty thing --Mithril! As light as a feather! And as hard as dragon scales! Let me see you put it on. Go on.
94	Bilbo	 Oh...M-my old Ring! Oh well… I sh-sh-should very much like, to hold it again, one last time.
94	Bilbo	 I’m sorry I brought this upon you my boy...I’m sorry that you must carry this burden. I’m sorry for everything!
96	Gandalf	 < voice over > We must hold this course west of the Misty Mountains for 40 days. If our luck holds the Gap of Rohan will still be open to us. From there our road turns east to Mordor.
97	Boromir	 Two, Three, Four, Five. Good, very good.
97	Aragorn	 Move your feet.
97	Merry	 That’s good, Pippin.
97	Pippin	 Thanks.
97	Boromir	 Faster
97	Gimli	 ‘Anyone was to ask for my opinion, which I note they’re not, I’d say we were taking the long way round. Gandalf, we could pass through the Mines of Moria. My cousin Balin would give us a royal welcome.
97	Gandalf	 No Gimli, I would not take the roads through Moria unless I had no other choice.
97	Boromir	 Come on. Good.
97	Pippin	 Aaaah!
97	Boromir	 Sorry!
97	Boromir	 Ahh!
97	Merry	 Get Him!
97	Pippin	 For the Shire!
97	Pippin	 Hold him! Hold him Merry!
97	Merry	 He got my arm! He got my arm!
97	Sam	 What is that?
97	Gimli	 Nothing, it’s just a whiff of cloud.
97	Boromir	 It’s moving fast…against the wind.
97	Legolas	 Crebain from Dunland!
97	Aragorn	 Hide!
97	Boromir	 Merry! Frodo!
97	Aragorn	 Come on, come on! Take cover!
97	Gandalf	 Spies of Saruman! The passage south is being watched. We must take the Pass of Caradhras.
97	Frodo	 Ungh!
97	Aragorn	 Frodo! < helps him to his feet >
98	Aragorn	 Boromir.
98	Boromir	 It is a strange fate we should suffer so much fear and doubt over so small a thing… such a little thing.
98	Aragorn	 Boromir! Give the Ring to Frodo.
98	Boromir	 < hands it to Frodo > As you wish. I care not.
99	Saruman	 So, Gandalf, you try to lead them over Caradhras. And if that fails, where then will you go? If the mountain defeats you will you risk a more dangerous road?
99	Saruman	" Cuiva nwalca Carnirasse; nai yarvaxea rasselya! (Wake up cruel Redhorn! May your horn be bloodstained!)"
100	Legolas	 There is a fell voice on the air.
100	Gandalf	 Its Saruman!
100	Aragorn	 He’s trying to bring down the mountain! Gandalf, we must turn back!
100	Gandalf	 No!
100	Gandalf	 Losto Caradhras, sedho, hodo, nuitho i 'ruith! (Sleep Caradhras, be still, lie still, hold your wrath!)
100	Saruman	" Cuiva nwalca Carnirasse; Nai yarvaxea rasselya; taltuva notto-carinnar! (Wake up cruel Redhorn! May your bloodstained horn fall upon enemy heads!)"
102	Boromir	 We must get off the mountain! Make for the Gap of Rohan and take the west road to my city!
102	Aragorn	 The Gap of Rohan takes us too close to Isengard!
102	Gimli	 If we cannot pass over a mountain, let us go under it. Let us go through the mines of Moria.
102	Saruman	 Moria. You fear to go into those mines. The dwarves delved too greedily and too deep. You know what they awoke in the darkness of Khazad-dum
102	Gandalf	 < grimly > Let the Ring bearer decide.
102	Gandalf	 Frodo?
102	Frodo	 We will go through the mines.
102	Gandalf	 So be it.
103	Gimli	 < in awe > The walls of Moria!
103	Frodo	 < gasp >
103	Gandalf	 Now, let’s see. Ithildin -- it mirrors only starlight and moonlight.
103	Gandalf	" It reads ""The doors of Durin - Lord of Moria. Speak friend and enter."""
103	Merry	 What do you suppose that means?
103	Gandalf	 Oh it’s quite simple. If you are a friend you speak the password and the doors will open.
103	Gandalf	 Annon Edhellen edro hi ammen! (Gate of the Elves open now for me!)
103	Gandalf	 Ando Eldarinwa a lasta quettanya, Fenda Casarinwa! (Gate of Elves listen to my word, Threshold of Dwarves!)
103	Aragorn	 < unhitches Bill’s bridle > The mines are no place for a pony, even one so brave as Bill.
103	Sam	 < sadly > Buh-bye Bill
103	Aragorn	 Go on, Bill, go on. Don’t worry Sam, he knows the way home.
103	Aragorn	 Do not disturb the water.
103	Gandalf	 < exasperated > Oh, it’s useless!
103	Frodo	" It’s a riddle. Speak ""friend"" and enter. What’s the Elvish word for friend?"
103	Gandalf	 Mellon
104	Gimli	 Soon master elf you will enjoy the fabled hospitality of the dwarves. Roaring fires, malt beer, ripe meat off the bone. This, my friend, is the home of my cousin Balin. And they call it a mine. A mine!
104	Boromir	 This is no mine, it’s a tomb!
104	Gimli	 Oh! No! Noooo!!!
104	Legolas	 Goblins!
104	Boromir	 We make for the Gap of Rohan. We should never have come here.
104	Boromir	 Now get out of here, get out!
105	Sam, Merry, and Pippin	 Frodo!
105	Sam	 Strider! < hacks at tentacle > Get off him!
105	Frodo	 aah!
105	Merry	 Aragorn!
105	Gandalf	 Into the Mines!
105	Boromir	 Legolas! Aim for his eye! Come on!
106	Gandalf	 We now have but one choice. We must face the long dark of Moria. Be on your guard. There are older and fouler things than orcs in the deep places of the world.
107	Gandalf	 Quietly now. It’s a four-day journey to the other side. Let us hope that our presence may go unnoticed.
107	Merry	 Pippin!
109	Gandalf	 I have no memory of this place
109	Pippin	 Are we lost?
109	Merry	 No.
109	Pippin	 I think we are.
109	Sam	 Shhh! Gandalf’s thinking.
109	Pippin	 Merry?
109	Merry	 What?
109	Pippin	 I’m hungry.
109	Frodo	 There’s something down there.
109	Gandalf	 It’s Gollum.
109	Frodo	 Gollum?
109	Gandalf	 He’s been following us for three days.
109	Frodo	 He escaped the dungeons of Barad-Dur!
109	Gandalf	 Escaped? Or set loose?
109	Gandalf	 He hates and loves the Ring, as he hates and loves himself. He will never be rid of his need for it.
109	Frodo	 It’s a pity Bilbo didn’t kill him when he had the chance!
109	Gandalf	 Pity? It was pity that stayed Bilbo’s hand. Many that live deserve death, and some that die deserve life. Can you give it to them, Frodo?
109	Gandalf	 Do not be too eager to deal out death in judgement. Even the very wise can not see all ends. My heart tells me that Gollum has some part to play yet, for good or ill, before this is over. The pity of Bilbo may rule the fate of many.
109	Frodo	 I wish the Ring had never come to me. I wish none of this had happened.
109	Gandalf	 So do all who live to see such times, but that is not for them to decide. All we have to decide is what to do with the time that is given to us. There are other forces at work in this world Frodo besides the will of evil. Bilbo was meant to find the Ring, in which case you also were meant to have it. And that is an encouraging thought.
109	Gandalf	 < looks towards one of the doorways > Ah! It’s that way.
109	Merry	 He’s remembered!
109	Gandalf	 No, but the air doesn’t smell so foul down here. If in doubt, Meriadoc, always follow your nose.
110	Gandalf	 Let me risk a little more light.
110	Gandalf	 Behold the great realm and dwarf city of Dwarrowdelf.
110	Sam	 Now there’s an eye opener and no mistake.
110	Gimli	 Haugh!
110	Gandalf	 Gimli!
111	Gimli	 No! No! < sob > No! < sob >
111	Gandalf	" < translates the runes on the tomb > ""Here lies Balin, son of Fundin, Lord of Moria."" He is dead then. Its as I feared."
111	Gimli	 < wails >
111	Legolas	 < to Aragorn > We must move on, we cannot linger!
111	Gandalf	" < reading > ""They have taken the bridge, and the second hall. We have barred the gates, but cannot hold them for long. The ground shakes. Drums, drums in the deep. < turns the page > We cannot get out. A Shadow moves in the dark. We cannot get out…They are coming."""
112	Gandalf	 < slams the book shut > Fool of a Took! Throw yourself in next time and rid us of your stupidity!
112	Sam	 Frodo! < Sting glows blue >
112	Legolas	 Orcs!
112	Aragorn	 < to the Hobbits > Get back! Stay close to Gandalf!
112	Boromir	 They have a cave troll.
112	Gimli	 Aarrgghhh!!! Let them come! There is one dwarf yet in Moria that still draws breath!
112	Sam	 < hits orcs with skillet > I think I’m getting the hang of this.
112	Frodo	 Aragorn? Aragorn!
112	Aragorn	 Frodo! Yaaahh!
112	Frodo	 < being stabbed > Ungh!
112	Sam	 Frodo? Frodo!
112	Merry and Pippin	 Yaahh!
112	Aragorn	 Oh no!
112	Sam	 He’s alive!
112	Frodo	 I’m all right, I’m not hurt.
112	Aragorn	 You should be dead! That spear would have skewered a wild boar.
112	Gandalf	 I think there’s more to this hobbit than meets the eye.
112	Gimli	 Mithril! You are full of surprises Master Baggins.
112	Gandalf	 To the bridge of Khazad-dum!
113	Boromir	 What is this new devilry?
113	Gandalf	 A Balrog-- a demon of the ancient world. This foe is beyond any of you. Run!
113	Aragorn	 Gandalf.
114	Gandalf	 Lead them on Aragorn. The bridge is near. < Aragorn resists > Do as I say! Swords are no more use here.
114	Legolas	 < beckons > Gandalf.
114	Boromir	 Merry! Pippin! Hoo-aah!
114	Aragorn	 Sam.
114	Gimli	 < holds up his hand > Nobody tosses a dwarf.
114	Gimli	 Not the beard!
114	Aragorn	 Stay there. Hold on. Hang on! Lean forward!
114	Legolas	 Come on!
115	Gandalf	 Over the bridge! Fly!
115	Gandalf	 You cannot pass!
115	Frodo	 Gandalf!
115	Gandalf	 I am the servant of the secret fire, wielder of the flame of Anor. The dark fire will not avail you! Flame of Udun!
115	Gandalf	 Go back to the shadow!
115	Gandalf	 YOU…SHALL NOT...PASS!!!
115	Boromir	 No, Frodo!
115	Frodo	 Gandaaaaalf!
115	Gandalf	 Fly you fools!
115	Frodo	 Noooooooooooooooo!!!!
115	Boromir	 Aragorn!
115	Frodo	 Noooooooooooo!!!
116	Aragorn	 Legolas, get them up.
116	Boromir	 Give them a moment for pity's sake.
116	Aragorn	 By nightfall these hills will be swarming with orcs! We must reach the Woods of Lothlorien. Come Boromir, Legolas, Gimli, get them up.
116	Aragorn	 < he reaches down and lifts Sam up > On your feet Sam. < looks around > Frodo? Frodo!
118	Gimli	 Stay close young hobbits! They say there’s a great sorceress lives in these woods, an elf-witch of terrible power. All who look upon her, fall under her spell...
118	Galadriel’s Voice	 < whispering echo > Frodo....
118	Gimli	 ... and are never seen again.
118	Galadriel’s Voice	 …Your coming to us… is as the footsteps of doom. You bring great evil here Ring bearer!
118	Sam	 Mr. Frodo?
118	Gimli	 Well, here is one dwarf she won't ensnare so easily. I have the eyes of a hawk and the ears of a fox!
118	Gimli	 Oh...
118	Haldir	 The dwarf breathes so loud we could have shot him in the dark.
118	Gimli	 Grrr....
118	Aragorn	 Haldir o Lórien. Henion aníron, boe ammen i dulu lîn. Boe ammen veriad lîn.
118	Gimli	 Aragorn, these woods are perilous! We should go back.
118	Haldir	 You have entered the realm of the Lady of the Wood. You cannot go back. Come, she is waiting.
120	Celeborn	 Eight that are here yet nine there were set out from Rivendell. Tell me where is Gandalf? For I much desire to speak with him.
120	Galadriel	 He has fallen into shadow.
120	Galadriel	 The quest stands upon the edge of a knife. Stray but a little and it will fail to the ruin of all.
120	Galadriel	 Yet hope remains while the company is true.
120	Galadriel	 Do not let your hearts be troubled. Go now and rest for you are weary with sorrow and much toil. Tonight you will sleep in peace. < whispers to Frodo in his mind > Welcome Frodo of the Shire. One who has seen the Eye!
121	Legolas	 < pensive > A lament for Gandalf.
121	Merry	 What do they say about him?
121	Legolas	 I have not the heart to tell you. For me the grief is still too near.
121	Aragorn	 Take some rest. These borders are well protected.
121	Boromir	 I will find no rest here. I heard her voice inside my head. She spoke of my father and the fall of Gondor. She said to me even now there is hope left. But I cannot see it. It is long since we had any hope.
121	Boromir	 My father is a noble man, but his rule is failing. And now our…our people lose faith. He looks to me to make things right and I would do it. I would see the glory of Gondor restored. < sigh > Have you ever seen it Aragorn? White tower of Ecthelion, glimmering like a spike of pearl and silver. It's banners caught high in the morning breeze. Have you ever been called home by the clear ringing of silver trumpets?
121	Aragorn	 I have seen the White City, long ago.
121	Boromir	 One day, our paths will lead us there. And the tower guards shall take up the call
122	Galadriel	 Will you look into the mirror?
122	Frodo	 What will I see?
122	Galadriel	 Even the wisest cannot tell. For the mirror shows many things.
122	Galadriel	 Things that were, things that are and some things… < empties the ewer > that have not yet come to pass.
122	Galadriel	 I know what it is you saw, for it is also in my mind. < speaks to Frodo telepathically > It is what will come to pass if you should fail. The Fellowship is breaking. It has already begun. He will try to take the Ring. You know of whom I speak. One by one it will destroy them all.
122	Frodo	 < telepathically > If you ask it of me, I will give you the One Ring.
122	Galadriel	 You offer it to me freely. I do not deny that my heart has greatly desired this.
122	Galadriel	 In place OF A DARK LORD, YOU WILL HAVE A QUEEN! NOT DARK BUT BEAUTIFUL AND TERRIBLE AS THE DAWN! TREACHEROUS AS THE SEA! STRONGER THAN THE FOUNDATIONS OF THE EARTH! ALL SHALL LOVE ME AND DISPAIR!
122	Galadriel	 I pass the test! I will diminish, and go into the West, and remain Galadriel.
122	Frodo	 I cannot do this alone.
122	Galadriel	 You are a Ring bearer, Frodo. To bear a Ring of power is to be alone. This task was appointed to you and if you do not find a way, no one will.
122	Frodo	 Then I know what I must do. It's just… I'm afraid to do it.
122	Galadriel	 Even the smallest person can change the course of the future.
123	Saruman	 Do you know how the Orcs first came into being? They were elves once, taken by the dark powers. Tortured and mutilated
123	Lurtz	 Saruman!
124	Saruman	 < to the troops > Hunt them down. Do not stop until they are found. You do not know pain. You do not know fear. You will taste man flesh!
124	Saruman	 < to Lurtz > One of the halflings carries something of great value. Bring them to me alive and unspoiled. Kill the others!
126	Galadriel	 Farewell, Frodo Baggins. I give you the light of Earendil, our most beloved star.
126	Galadriel	 Namarie.
127	Galadriel	 May it be a light for you in dark places, when all other lights go out.
130	Aragorn	 Frodo, the Argonath! Long have I desired to look upon the kings of old. My kin.
131	Aragorn	 We cross the lake at nightfall. Hide the boats and continue on foot. We approach Mordor from the north.
131	Gimli	 Oh, yes?! It's just a simple matter of finding our way through Emyn Muil? An impassable labyrinth of razor sharp rocks! And after that, it gets even better! < Pippin looks up, alarmed > Festering, stinking marshlands far as the eye can see!
131	Aragorn	 That is our road. I suggest you take some rest and recover your strength master dwarf.
131	Gimli	 Recover my…?! Phrrrrr...
131	Legolas	 < quietly to Aragorn > We should leave now.
131	Aragorn	 No. Orcs patrol the eastern shore. We must wait for cover of darkness.
131	Legolas	 It is not the eastern shore that worries me. A shadow and a threat has been growing in my mind. Something draws near...I can feel it!
131	Gimli	 No dwarf need recover strength! < to Pippin > Pay no heed to that, young hobbit.
131	Merry	 Where's Frodo?
132	Boromir	 None of us should wander alone, you least of all. So much depends on you. Frodo?
132	Boromir	" I know why you seek solitude. You suffer; I see it day by day. You sure you do not suffer needlessly? There are other ways, Frodo, other paths that we might take."
132	Frodo	 I know what you would say. And it would seem like wisdom but for the warning in my heart.
132	Boromir	 Warning? Against what? We're all afraid, Frodo. But to let that fear drive us to destroy what hope we have. Don't you see that is madness?
132	Frodo	 There is no other way!
132	Boromir	 I ask only for the strength to defend my people! < throws the gathered wood to the ground > If you would but lend me the Ring...
132	Frodo	 No. < steps back >
132	Boromir	 Why do you recoil? I am no thief.
132	Frodo	 You are not yourself.
132	Boromir	 What chance do you think you have? They will find you! They will take the Ring and you will beg for death before the end!
132	Boromir	 Fool!
132	Boromir	 It is not yours save by unhappy chance. It could have been mine! < tackles Frodo > It should be mine! Give it to me!
132	Boromir	 Give it to me!
132	Frodo	 No!
132	Boromir	 Give me… Give me the Ring!
132	Frodo	 Nurgh…ugh!
132	Boromir	 < looks around desperately > I see your mind. You will take the Ring to Sauron! You will betray us! You go to your death and the death of us all! Curse you! Curse you! And all the halflings!
132	Boromir	 Frodo?...Frodo?...what have I done?...please...Frodo!
133	Boromir	 < in the background > Frodo, I'm sorry! Oh no!
134	Aragorn	 Frodo?
134	Frodo	 < startled > Huh?! It has taken Boromir.
134	Aragorn	 < intensely > Where is the Ring?
134	Frodo	 Stay away! < scrambles up and retreats from Aragorn. Aragorn comes after him >
134	Aragorn	 Frodo!
134	Aragorn	 I swore to protect you!
134	Frodo	 Can you protect me from yourself?!
134	Frodo	 Would you destroy it?
134	The Ring	 Aragorn...Aragorn…Elessar...
134	Aragorn	 I would have gone with you to the end, into the very fires of Mordor.
134	Frodo	 I know. Look after the others, especially Sam. He will not understand.
134	Aragorn	 Go on Frodo. < draws out his sword > Run. Run!
135	Sam	 Mr.Frodo!!!
135	Lurtz	 < to his troops > Find the Halfling! Find the Halfling!
135	Aragorn	 < jumps onto the Uruk-Hai > Elendil!!!!!
135	Legolas	 Aragorn! Go!
135	Merry	 Frodo!
135	Pippin	 < beckoning > Hide here quick! Come on!
135	Pippin	 < to Merry > What’s he doin'?
135	Merry	 He's leavin’.
135	Pippin	 No! < runs out to Frodo >
135	Merry	 Pippin! < comes after him >
135	Merry	 < quietly > Run Frodo! Go!
135	Merry	 Hey! Hey you! Over here!
135	Pippin	 Hey!
135	Merry	 Over here!
135	Pippin	 < waving his arms > This way!
135	Pippin	 Its working!
135	Merry	 I know its working! Run!
135	Legolas	 The Horn of Gondor!
135	Aragorn	 Boromir!
135	Boromir	 < to the hobbits > Run! Run!
135	Merry and Pippin	 Shire!!!!!
135	Aragorn	 No! < runs up and kneels near Boromir >
135	Boromir	 They took the little ones.
135	Aragorn	 Be still.
135	Boromir	 Frodo, where is Frodo?
135	Aragorn	 I let Frodo go.
135	Boromir	 Then you did what I could not. I tried to take the Ring from him.
135	Aragorn	 The Ring is beyond our reach now.
135	Boromir	 Forgive me, I did not see it. I have failed you all.
135	Aragorn	 No, Boromir, you fought bravely! You have kept your honor. < reaches out to pull the arrows from Boromir >
135	Boromir	 Leave it! It is over. The world of men will fall, and all will come to darkness… and my city to ruin.
135	Aragorn	 I do not know what strength is in my blood, but I swear to you I will not let the white city fall, nor our people fail!
135	Boromir	 Our people? Our people.
135	Boromir	 I would have followed you my brother, my captain, my king!
135	Aragorn	 Be at peace, son of Gondor. < bends and kisses Boromir on the brow >
136	Sam	 Frodo!
136	Frodo	 I wish the Ring had never come to me. I wish none of this had happened.
136	Gandalf	 So do all who live to see such times but that is not for them to decide. All you have to decide is what to do with the time that is given to you.
136	Sam	 Frodo no! Frodo! Mr. Frodo!
136	Frodo	 < quietly > No Sam. < continues to paddle away >
136	Frodo	 Go back Sam! I’m going to Mordor alone.
136	Sam	 Of course you are, and I’m coming with you!
136	Frodo	 You can’t swim! Sam!
136	Frodo	 Sam!!!
136	Sam	" < dripping wet > I made a promise, Mr. Frodo. A promise! ""Don’t you leave him Samwise Gamgee."" And I don’t mean to! I don’t mean to."
136	Frodo	 Oh Sam! < hug > Come on.
137	Legolas	 Hurry! Frodo and Sam have reached the eastern shore.
137	Legolas	 You mean not to follow them?
137	Aragorn	 Frodo’s fate is no longer in our hands.
137	Gimli	 Then it has all been in vain! The Fellowship has failed.
137	Aragorn	 < puts his hands on their shoulders > Not if we hold true to each other. We will not abandon Merry and Pippin to torment and death. Not while we have strength left. Leave all that can be spared behind. We travel light. Let’s hunt some orc!
137	Gimli	 Yes!!! Haha!
138	Frodo	 Mordor. I hope the others find a safer route.
138	Sam	 Strider will look after them.
138	Frodo	 I don’t suppose we’ll ever see them again.
138	Sam	 We may yet, Mr. Frodo. We may.
138	Frodo	 < turns, smiling > Sam, I’m glad you’re with me.
